Are you serious?
此話當真？
So, what will you do?
那麼，你有何打算？
You are a gardener that maintains our flower garden, are you not?
你是照料朕花園的園丁，對吧？
What a shrewd man he is.
真是精明的大人
How ironic.
說來諷刺
No matter how hard I worked
不論我多麼努力
with the pen or the sword, I only became better than average.
我的智謀和武藝 也不過就比普通人好上一點
But my appearance surpassed that of anyone else.
唯有外貌天生就超群出眾
The things you really want…
自己真正想要的東西
will rarely be yours.
就越是難以得到
I struggled with this back in the day,
雖然以前總是難以釋懷
but now, I understand my role.
但現在已經能看開了
A sweet gaze, a sweet voice…
動人的眼神、甜美的嗓音
I'll use whatever tools I have to my advantage.
我就盡可能善用這些出眾的特質吧
I know that
我很明白
I'm just a child flailing in the palms of the Emperor.
我終究不過是 被皇帝玩弄於股掌中的孩子而已
As you will, My Lord.
遵旨
I'll manage the rear palace. I'll do anything.
就算是管理後宮，我也會竭盡所能
This is the only way to choose my own path.
這是我能夠選擇自己道路的唯一方法
VERDIGRIS HOUSE
（綠青館）
THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、組織名均為虛構 與任何特定事件或現象無關）
I don't need this much, Big Sis.
我不需要這麼多啦，姐姐
Sure, sure. Take this, and that.
好啦…這個拿著，那個也拿著
Oh, take this too.
對了，還有這個
I won't be using lipstick.
我沒有在用唇脂啊
Don't be ridiculous! You should make yourself look presentable.
妳說什麼傻話！ 至少也要打扮得像樣一點
Only courtesans dress up to go to work, you know…
要精心打扮再上工的 也就只有娼妓之類的了吧？
I want to mix my medicine herbs… Ouch!
我想去調藥了…好痛！
Hey, you got a good job in the court.
妳呀，好不容易 得到了一份在宮廷裡的好差事
Don't you want to become a person worthy of that position?
難道不想讓自己成為 配得上那個職位的人嗎？
You have to be grateful for what you're given in life.
如果不心懷感恩生活的話
Otherwise, even the best customers will run away!
這麼難得的貴客也會跑走的喔
Big Sis Meimei's words are persuasive.
梅梅姐姐的話很有說服力
She's old enough to consider retiring as a courtesan,
以娼妓而言 她也到了該考慮引退的年紀
but she remains popular because
但至今依然很受歡迎
she has the intellect to
不僅是因為擅長歌藝與棋藝
entertain her guests with song, chess, and go.
也有能取悅賓客的知性
Maomao.
貓貓
You packed heavy!
行李還真多呢
Big Sis Pairin, Big Sis Joka.
白鈴姐姐、女華姐姐
I'm glad you got a nice job.
能到好地方工作真是太好了
Go earn a lot, you hear?
要多賺一點喔
Okay.
我明白
It'd be helpful if you could bring some high-paying guests.
如果能帶一些貴客過來就太好了
Find a rich, good husband, okay?
要找個有錢的好夫君喔
Someone with a lot of vigor, okay?
拜託妳找些精力旺盛的人吧
My new workplace, or rather,
新的職場，或者說…
the workplace I'm returning to is the rear palace inside the court.
我要重新就職的場所 是宮廷中叫做後宮的地方
It's an all-women's world made to bear the Emperor's children.
那是為了替皇帝繁衍後嗣的女性花園
I was only supposed to be a lowly maid,
我本該只是個不起眼的婢女
but I got noticed for solving the serial deaths of the Emperor's children.
但我解開了皇子接連死亡的謎團 而因此受到注意
I got promoted to become Lady Gyokuyou's attendant,
被晉升為玉葉娘娘的侍女
then got roped into all kinds of tricky business as a food taster.
還成為了試毒人 被捲進各式各樣的麻煩事
Many things happened and I was dismissed from my position.
之後發生了很多事，我被解僱了
I didn't think I'd be serving the court again.
但沒想到又會再度回到宮裡
I got lured by the plant worms,
我敗給了冬蟲夏草的誘惑
but it might've been a thoughtless decision.
現在想來，也許太過輕率了些
Of course, I'm extremely fortunate compared to others.
當然，跟其他人比起來我幸運多了
I'm a bit worried about
留下老爹一個人
leaving behind Old Man to do live-in work again,
回到宮裡工作，雖然多少有些擔心
but the rules will be less strict than they used to be,
但跟之前比起來，規定寬鬆許多
so I won't be considered "missing" like before.
也不像之前一樣是失蹤狀態
Old Man said, "Do as you like," but…
老爹也說 “照妳的心意去做吧”，但是…
What did he mean by that?
那到底是什麼意思？
I'm home.
我回來了
Wow, you got a lot of gifts.
拿到很多東西呢
What should I do?
該怎麼辦？
I definitely need my bowls and mortars, and I need my notebook.
研缽和搗藥棒是一定要帶的 還有筆記簿
I can't bring even less underwear…
褻衣也不能再少了…
Maomao.
貓貓
You probably shouldn't bring those things.
那些大概不能帶進去喔
If you bring those things even though you're not a physician,
畢竟妳不是醫官 如果妳帶了那些東西進去
they'll think you're plotting a murder by poison.
可能會被懷疑妳要下毒殺人呢
Don't look like that.
別露出這種表情
You decided this yourself.
這是妳決定好的事情
It's too late for take-backs now.
事到如今反悔可不行喔
Really?
真的嗎？
If you get permission in small batches, there are some things you can bring.
只要能慢慢得到許可 有些東西還是能帶進去的
Get ready and go to bed.
早點準備好就睡覺吧
Tomorrow's your first day.
明天可是第一天工作
Okay…
我知道了
What is this? You haven't done this in a long time.
怎麼了？好久沒這樣了
I thought you weren't a child anymore.
不是說已經不是小孩子了嗎？
Well, it's cold.
很冷嘛
I'll miss you, you know.
又要變得冷清了呢
It'll be okay. This time, I can come home whenever I want.
不會啦，這次隨時都可以回家嘛
That's true. Come back anytime, okay?
也是，想回來時就回來吧
I don't have a mother.
我沒有母親
But I have a kind father, a nosy grandmother,
但我有個慈祥的老爹和煩人的嬤嬤
and many lively older sisters.
還有一群活潑熱鬧的姐姐
I can come home anytime I want.
我隨時都可以回來
I'm sorry for the wait, Sir Jinshi.
抱歉讓您久等了，壬氏大人
Please take care of our girl.
我們家的孩子就麻煩您照顧了
We made sure she's all moisturized and supple.
我們可是將她打理的水嫩飽滿呢
Don't forget, Maomao.
妳知道的吧，貓貓？
I know. High-paying customers, right?
我知道啦，出手大方的貴客，對吧？
All right, off you go!
沒錯，妳可以走了
What a stressful morning.
一大早就累死人了
All right, let's go.
那我們走吧
Sure.
喔
Be careful.
保重
I'm off.
我走了
She's beautiful!
好漂亮啊
I've never seen her at the Verdigris House.
綠青館竟然有這樣的姑娘啊？
It's your fault, Sir Jinshi.
都是壬氏大人害的
-They're all looking at us. -That's because you're…
-大家全都盯著我們瞧 -那是因為妳…
-What is it? -Nothing.
-我怎麼了？ -沒怎麼了
Good work, all. Can we go now?
辛苦各位了，可以走了嗎？
Yes, sir!
是！
Apothecary. Put your regular freckled face on while you're here.
藥師，在這裡就照以往那樣畫雀斑吧
Huh?
什麼？
All right, sir.
我知道了
Hey, did you hear? A rear palace manager
聽說了嗎？後宮總管
bought out a courtesan from the Verdigris House!
好像幫一名綠青館的娼妓贖身呢！
The Verdigris House?
綠青館？
That's where the Three Princesses are, right?
是有三姬的那個綠青館？
The Verdigris House…?
綠青館嗎？
What is he doing?
這個人在搞什麼？
Where are we?
這裡是？
-This is my house. -Why…?
-我家 -什麼？
This is your new workplace.
這裡就是妳的新職場
Sir Gaoshun.
高順大人
I had assumed that I would be returning to the rear palace…
我還以為我會回到後宮…
You've already quit once.
畢竟曾把妳辭退過
It would be hard for you to return.
沒辦法那麼簡單就回去的
You will be working at the outer court this time.
今後妳就在外廷工作吧
The outer court…
外廷…
Yes.
對
The rear palace, where you were, is the inner court.
小貓妳之前待的後宮屬於內廷
The outer court is just outside of that.
內廷的外圍就是外廷
It's home to many government offices. I'll show you around later.
這裡是各種官署的所在地 我之後會帶妳熟悉環境
Welcome home. You must be freezing.
歡迎回來，你們肯定凍壞了吧？
I'm the attendant, Suiren.
我是侍女水蓮
You must be Xiaomao.
妳就是小貓吧？
Yes, ma'am.
是的
Xiaomao?
小貓？
There are separate buildings for the office and living quarters.
書房和私室是兩棟不同的樓房
Beyond this point is Young Master's room…
這前面就是少爺的房間了
Young Master?
少爺？
You're probably fine.
妳的話應該沒關係吧
This is about the same size room that I was using in the Jade Pavilion.
跟我在翡翠宮時的房間差不多大呢
Now if this had a stove and a well nearby…
如果這裡有爐灶 附近有水井就好了…
Seems like
不過…
this room is too fancy for a live-in maidservant.
以住在宮裡的婢女來說 這房間也太過豪華了
-Xiaomao? -Yes, ma'am!
-小貓？ -是
I don't intend on you being a servant here.
我並沒有打算讓妳當婢女
What?
什麼？
I said you'd be working at the outer court, no?
我說過會讓妳在外廷當差的吧？
You'll be taking the court lady exam.
妳要參加女官考試
The court lady exam?
女…女官考試？
Clothes made out of cotton?
用棉布做的衣服？
What special treatment I'm getting.
待遇還真是不錯呢
Good morning, Ms. Suiren.
早安，水蓮大人
Good morning, Xiaomao.
早安，小貓
You're up early. Good on you.
妳起得真早，很不錯喔
I'm here to help.
我來幫忙
No, I'm almost done here.
沒關係，我差不多做好了
Can you just help carry these?
可以麻煩妳幫忙端出去嗎？
Yes, ma'am.
好的
-What about the other attendants? -We have none.
-其他侍女呢？ -只有我們喔
The office is fine, but we can't have people
書房倒還沒關係
for his private rooms,
房間可沒辦法拜託其他人打理
let alone his meals.
更別提幫少爺準備膳食了
So you do everything on your own?
所以一直都只有您在打點嗎？
We've had new girls in the past,
以前也找過好幾個新的姑娘
but there's been incidents, and we have to let them go.
但發生了一些事，都沒能繼續做下去
Was he drugged with an aphrodisiac? Or theft?
他被下了催情藥嗎？還是失竊呢？
No one would enjoy
在衣櫃裡發現
finding underwear they've never seen in their wardrobe.
從未見過的褻衣 任誰都會感到不適的吧
What?
什麼？
And instead of using thread, it was woven with hair!
而且還不是用針線 而是用毛髮編織成的
He has it rough, doesn't he?
還真是不得了呢
He sure does.
可不是嘛
Wake up, Young Master.
少爺，請您起床了
It's time for breakfast.
該用早膳了
He's being seductive for no reason…
散發著無謂的誘惑力…
Now I get why only Sir Gaoshun and Ms. Suiren can enter this room.
我明白為何只有高順大人 和水蓮大人才能進到這房間了
A woman will get hot and steamy from his sex appeal,
若是女人的話 恐怕會受不了誘惑而血氣上頭
and a man might try and do something.
男人的話應該會直接撲倒他吧
How unfortunate that he attracts all these sinful thoughts.
真是位罪孽深重的大人
He's like an insect in heat.
就像是發情期的蟲子一樣
If I collect this eunuch's smell and make a love potion, it might sell!
把這個宦官的體味收集起來 製成媚藥的話，也許能賣錢呢
If you're fine with it, I'll make them prepare a new room for you.
妳願意的話 我可以派人幫妳準備新房間
What is he talking about?
他在說什麼？
I'm confused, but maybe it's a chance to get a stove and a well?
雖然不太懂 但或許是有爐灶或水井的機會？
If you want to say something, just say it!
有話又不明說，我怎麼會知道？
I can probably find access to a stove…
總而言之，也許能用爐灶了…
Then, perhaps a stable with a well nearby.
那麼，我想要附近有水井的馬廄
-A stable? -Yes, sir.
-馬廄？ -是的，馬廄
No. I won't get you that.
馬廄不行
All right. Let's start the tour.
我帶妳走一圈吧
Yes, thank you.
好的，麻煩您了
Sir Jinshi had to stay home.
壬氏大人不幸得留下
He's always wasting time at the rear palace, so I thought he had no work,
他總是待在後宮 本來還以為是個閒人
but apparently, he's a very busy man.
但似乎意外地很忙
There are many soldiers on the eastern side beyond this point.
這裡往東的地方有許多武官
So avoid this area if you can.
請盡量不要靠近
I understand.
我明白了
The palace I was shown around was very large,
他介紹的宮殿都很龐大
with so many buildings and departments that
建物的名字和官署的名稱
I couldn't count them on my fingers and toes.
用上手腳都數不完
Could I really memorize them all?
我能記得起來嗎？
I have terrible memory when it concerns things I have no interest in.
我對沒興趣的東西 記憶力連一般人都不如啊
This is the Director of Waters.
這裡是都水監
This office deals with all irrigation businesses like rivers and embankments.
這是負責 河川和堤防等水利事務的官署
I see…
原來如此
The rear palace had more ingredients that I could make medicine with.
果然還是後宮 能拿來製藥的材料比較多呢
My guess is that Old Man transported them when he worked there.
應該是老爹那時候移植進去的吧？
Xiaomao.
小貓
If you become a court lady, this will be your workplace.
如果妳成了女官 職場就是在外廷了啊
Yes, sir…
是
A court lady, huh?
女官嗎？
Hello Xiaomao. Perfect timing.
小貓，妳來得正是時候
Can you carry the charcoal to the office?
能麻煩妳把木炭拿去書房嗎？
Yes, ma'am.
好的
Excuse me.
打擾了
So this is Sir Jinshi's office…
這裡就是壬氏大人的書房啊…
It's not flashy, but everything is high quality.
稱不上豪華，但全都是上等貨呢
Just how high-class is that "Young Master"?
這位“少爺”的官位究竟有多高啊？
Observing the newcomer, huh?
在觀察新來的人嗎？
Bad vibes.
感覺真差
A court lady for the outer court is basically a clerk.
外廷的女官職務類似於書記官
They have certifications, a good family, and a good education.
必須具備資格，擁有家世與教養
They're not like the palace women of the rear palace with diverse backgrounds.
跟後宮聚集的宮女大不相同
With such position comes pride.
所以自尊心也比較高
That's why
因為如此
they don't need to clean. It's not their job, after all.
所以也沒必要在工作之外特地打掃
Just who do you think you are?
妳以為妳是誰？
They must be well-fed to grow this large.
吃得好所以也長得好呢
Hey, I'm talking to you! Why does someone like you work directly for Sir Jinshi?
妳有在聽嗎？就妳這姑娘 憑什麼在壬氏大人直屬下做事？
I guess staying quiet would upset them even more.
就算閉著嘴 也只是讓她們火上加油嗎？
Does this mean you are jealous of my position?
也就是說，妳們在忌妒我嗎？
Cut it out, will you?
竟敢放肆！
I worded it wrong.
我說錯話了呢
Can't be helped.
沒辦法了
You think I'm getting special treatment?
妳以為我是受到特別關照嗎？
Of course not, right?
怎麼可能會有那種事呢？
Why would a heavenly maiden like him pay any attention
那位像天女一樣的大人 怎麼可能會把我這樣的醜女
to a plain girl like me?
當成對象呢？
You think that the man you respect so much has such bad taste?
各位心中的貴人會如此飢不擇食嗎？
In a place with plenty of abalone and boar meat,
眼前明明有著鮑魚和豬肉
he would eat a scrawny piece of chicken?
怎麼會想要去吃削掉肉的雞骨呢？
That would mean he's got a "unique preference" for girls.
如果是那樣的話 難道他有“特殊癖好”嗎？
That's not for me to understand.
那我就不清楚了
So that's his taste, huh?
原來他有“特殊癖好”嗎？
I see, a "unique preference…"
原來是這樣啊，“特殊癖好”啊…
Of course not!
怎麼可能會有那種事！
Exactly!
對啊
Then, why were you hired?
那麼，大人為什麼會雇用妳？
This is the reason.
原因是這個
I experimented with burn medicine the other day,
前幾天用手臂來測試燒傷藥
so my arm is in a pretty bad state.
所以才會皮焦肉爛的
It stings!
好痛！
The beautiful heavenly maiden
那位美若天仙的大人
also has the heart of one.
就連心地都有如天女一般
He even provides someone like me with a way to feed myself.
所以才會施捨我這樣的人一口飯吃
Let's go.
我們走吧
Finally.
總算結束了
A "unique preference…"
“特殊癖好”…
Are you always getting caught up in fights like that?
妳經常像那樣被人糾纏嗎？
And what did you show on your left arm…
話說，妳為何舉起左手…
All right, then. I'll be off to clean the next place.
那麼，我去打掃下個地方了
And how's your studying going?
妳書念得如何？
Scatter, scatter…
撤了…
Hey!
喂！
Xiaomao…
小貓
Quiet, all right?
小聲一點
And finally, the day of the exams arrived…
就這樣，考試的日子到了
Why did you fail?
妳怎麼會沒考過？
Why did he think I'd pass?
你怎麼覺得我考得過？
Maomao became Jinshi's personal room maidservant.
貓貓成了壬氏的貼身婢女
What shall we do?
該怎麼辦？
What shall we do, indeed?
該怎麼辦呢？
The area beyond this point is forbidden for people like you.
前方不是妳可以擅闖的地方
Can't she tell me before punching me?
打人之前不能先講一聲嗎？
The scent of sandalwood and a particular bitter aroma…
檀香的香味，還帶有一點獨特的苦味
The Board of Military, huh?
軍府嗎？
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集預告）
Next episode, "The New Pure Concubine."
下一集，《新人淑妃》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻譯：歐德慧